Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Library of Congress
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Manuscripts, 1859-1892 and undated (Box 1)
  - Notes and Flanges.—No. 1., about 1888; loc.04235; xxx.00410; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder "Drift Sands")
    Manuscript scrap containing two trial titles and two poetic lines, with corrections. Although Whitman never published a poem with either of these titles, this and several other closely related manuscripts seem to constitute working drafts for the couplet "As idly drifting down the ebb, / Such ripples, half-caught voices, echo from the shore," which appears before the final paragraph of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ). Most of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads was drawn from three previously published pieces (A Backward Glance on My Own Road [ 1884 ], How I Made a Book [ 1886 ], and My Book and I [ 1887 ]). The couplet, however, was not part of any of those earlier essays.
  - [Ripple and echoes from the], about 1888; loc.04236; xxx.00410; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder "Drift Sands")
    Manuscript containing draft versions of lines that appear before the final paragraph of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads as the couplet "As idly drifting down the ebb, / Such ripples, half-caught voices, echo from the shore." First published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads was mostly made up of material from three previously published pieces: A Backward Glance on My Own Road ( 1884 ), How I Made a Book ( 1886 ), and My Book and I ( 1887 ). The couplet, however, was not part of any of those earlier essays.
  - Drift Sands, about 1888; loc.04240; xxx.00410; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder "Drift Sands")
    This manuscript of two draft lines and title is closely related to several other manuscripts, all of which seem to constitute working drafts for the lines that appear before the final paragraph of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads as the couplet "As idly drifting down the ebb, / Such ripples, half-caught voices, echo from the shore." First published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads was mostly made up of material from three previously published pieces: A Backward Glance on My Own Road ( 1884 ), How I Made a Book ( 1886 ), and My Book and I ( 1887 ). The couplet, however, was not part of any of those earlier essays.
  - Gossip at Dusk, undated; loc.00367; xxx.00648; poetry 3 leaves 4 x 14 to 20 x 12.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Gossip at Dusk)
    Drafts of lines entitled Gossip at Dusk. The relationship to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - Maize-Tassels, undated; loc.00368; xxx.00649; poetry 1 leaf 14.5 x 13.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder Maize-Tassels)
    A draft of a poem entitled Maize-Tassels. Written at the top of the manuscript is the note, "White Horse notes." The relationship of this manuscript to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [the strong right], undated; loc.00369; xxx.00650; poetry 1 leaf 20.5 x 12.5 cm handwritten (Box 1, Folder The Strong Right Hand)
    A couple of trial lines for an unrealized poem, beginning "the strong right hand." These lines have no known relationship to Whitman's published work.
  - paths of rhyme, 1857-1881; loc.05618; xxx.00526; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    The sentiments about the poet and versification are present in the revised Preface, 1855, to first issue of 'Leaves of Grass,' published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ). Grier dates this scrap from 1857, and the verso has a printed date of 185-.
  - truly the things, 1855-1856; loc.05620; xxx.00048; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    The phrase "commonest, cheapest, nearest, easiest" first appears in the 1856 Leaves of Grass in the poem ultimately titled Song of Myself. This phrase echoes the scrap's phrase, "things commonest & cheapest, nearest to us of all our daily lives."
  - Roundly considered, 1880-1881; loc.05621; xxx.00473; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    Much of the language of this note is reproduced in the essay Five Thousand Poems, first published in The Critic, April 16, 1887, on page 187, and again in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - Distinctive and without relation, 1887; loc.05623; xxx.00473; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
  - [Light], undated; loc.00370; xxx.00651; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    A draft of lines beginning "Light/ Lives, water, light/ and darkness." These lines have no known relationship to Whitman's published work.
  - [all birth and growth], undated; loc.00375; xxx.00652; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    Two scraps of paper held together because of treatment by a collector or archivist. These lines have no known relationship to Whitman's published work.
  - [Like the young eagle], undated; loc.00371; xxx.00653; poetry 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and Unidentified)
    Three scraps of paper held together with draft lines bearing an unknown relationship to Whitman's published work.
  - The appearance, 1890-1891; loc.05302; xxx.00871; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder Spectacle Inside the Opera House)
    This item is part of a draft of the article The Opera that Whitman wrote under the pseudonym Mose Velsor of Brooklyn. The Opera was first published in Life Illustrated, 10 November 1855. The article was collected in New York Dissected, ed. Emory Holloway and Ralph Adimari (New York: Rufus Rockwell Wilson, 1936 ), 18-23.
  - But only pond-babble, 1890-1891; loc.05256; xxx.00459; xxx.00555; prose correspondence handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder Only Mulleins and Bumble-bees)
    The notes on the recto are prefatory in nature and reflect the spirit of the preface to Whitman's 1891 Good-Bye My Fancy 2d Annex to Leaves of Grass. The exact phrase, "the mullein and the bumble-bee" is on page 36 of the section entitled Gathering the Corn of Good-Bye My Fancy. On the verso is a partial letter from Whitman to unknown friends.
  - Two or three memories, December 13, 1883; loc.05304; xxx.00474; xxx.00588; xxx.00870; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder Notes and Memories)
    This item refers to the Italian tenor Giovanni Matteo Mario's death on December 11,1883. Whitman referred to Mario in Specimen Days & Collect, published in 1882-1883, in the passages entitled Plays and Operas, Too, The Old Bowery, and Old Actors, Singers, Shows, etc., in New York.
  - That there should be, 1875-1888; loc.05650; xxx.00473; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder [Before 1890?], on the nature of poetry)
    This manuscript contributed to the last part of the section Five Thousand Poems in November Boughs published in 1888 (retained within November Boughs in Complete Prose Works [ 1892 ]).
  - from the traditional commencement, 1868-1871; loc.02806; xxx.00496; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Memoranda (Old and New) of Camden)
    The note in this manuscript bears resemblance to the general theme of the poem Passage to India, which was published in the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass, and was retained in all the subsequent editions.
  - from the traditional commencement, 1868-1871; loc.02806; xxx.00496; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Memoranda (Old and New) of Camden)
  - from the traditional commencement, 1868-1871; loc.02806; xxx.00496; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Memoranda (Old and New) of Camden)
  - Note A * While, 1880-1888; loc.07036; xxx.00473; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Untitled and unidentified)
    The passage in this manuscript appears in the section Five Thousand Poems of November Boughs, published in 1888 (retained within November Boughs in Complete Prose Works [ 1892 ]).
  - In mem. of A.L., 1865; loc.07040; xxx.00217; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Abraham Lincoln)
    The notes contained in this manuscript, significantly titled "In Mem. of A.L." ("In Memory of Abraham Lincoln") are focused on the sense of collective grieving for the death of Lincoln, a founding theme for the poem When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom'd, initially published in Sequel to Drum Taps, issued by Gibson Brothers in the fall of 1865 and bound with Drum Taps. The poem made its first appearance in the text of Leaves of Grass in 1867.
  - For funeral piece, 1865; loc.07041; xxx.00217; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Abraham Lincoln)
    This manuscript, significantly titled "For Funeral piece A.L." ("For Funeral piece A.L."), is composed of a short note which can be read as a general outline of the poem When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom'd, followed by some lines of poetry that bear resemblance with section eleven of the same poem. The poem was initially published in Sequel to Drum Taps, issued by Gibson Brothers in the fall of 1865 and bound with Drum Taps. The poem made its first appearance in the text of Leaves of Grass in 1867.
- Notes and Memoranda, 1856-1888 and undated (Box 1, Box 2)
  - [How will it do for figure?], about 1856; loc.00372; xxx.00654; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder on slavery)
    Notes and draft lines of a work concerning slavery. The relationship of these lines to Whitman's published work is unknown. On the verso is a page from the November, 1856 Christian Examiner.
  - [Farewell my brethren], about 1873; loc.00373; xxx.00118; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    On the recto is a cancelled draft of lines from Song of the Redwood Tree, first published in 1873. On the verso is a meditation on the war, of which the connection to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [Blacks], about 1873; loc.00374; xxx.00797; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    Held together with two other scraps of paper is a note regarding the skill of black "pilots in the US ships" during the attack on Charleston. The relationship of this manuscript to Whitman's published works is unclear.
  - [Echoes & Drift], 1879-1882; loc.05541; xxx.00458; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    This manuscript contains what could possibly be trial titles for Specimen Days & Collect published in 1882-1883.
  - For Note, 1863-1875; loc.01552; xxx.00502; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder [1865 or before], war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    In this manuscript, entitled "For Note," Whitman seems to be drafting an introductory note for Memoranda During the War, published in 1875-1876. Although the note does not appear verbatim in Memoranda, some passages of this manuscript bear resemblance to the introductory paragraphs in which Whitman reflects on the impossibility of writing a complete and accurate history of the war and offers the rationale for his decision to record a "few glimpses" of "the Hospital part of the drama from '61 to '65."
  - For War Memoranda, 1863-1875; loc.01553; xxx.00502; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder [1865 or before], war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    This manuscript contains preparatory material for Memoranda During the War, published in 1875-1876. (Although the note does not appear verbatim in Memoranda, the fact that Whitman titles the manuscript "for war memoranda note," using a different pen, clearly indicates that he thought of using the note for the book.) On the verso is a draft of the section titled An Afternoon Scene published in Specimen Days & Collect, see the entry for loc.06100.
  - ? the sky, 1863-1881; loc.06100; xxx.00974; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder [1865 or before], war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    This manuscript contains a draft of the section titled An Afternoon Scene published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) and later retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso is preparatory material for Memoranda During the War, see the entry for loc.01553.
  - Make a conclusion, 1863-1875; loc.01554; xxx.00975; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder [1865 or before], war and hospital notes and memoranda)
    This manuscript contains a short note with two war scenes (the homeward bound Armies at Washington and the disbanding, and the first onset and alarm) that Whitman hypothesized to use as a conclusion and an opening for Memoranda During the War ( 1875-1876 ). The scenes did not appear in these locations, but were used, still in Memoranda, in the section titled The Ensuing Three Months—The National Uprising and Volunteering. The scenes were also included within National Uprising and Volunteering published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) and later retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Tramps & Strikes, 1879-1882; loc.05251; xxx.00539; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder The Tramp and Strike Questions)
    This prose scrap, titled Tramps & Strikes, varies in its wording from the undelivered address The Tramp and Strike Question. Nonetheless, it reflects themes present in the address eventually published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ).
  - for Tramp and strike question, 1879-1882; loc.05252; xxx.00539; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder The Tramp and Strike Questions)
    This prose scrap, titled for Tramp & Strike Question, varies in its wording from the undelivered address The Tramp and Strike Question. Nonetheless, it reflects themes present in the address eventually published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ).
  - for the Strike & Tramp questions, 1879-1882; loc.05258; xxx.00539; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder The Tramp and Strike Questions)
    This prose scrap, titled for The Strike & Tramp questions, varies in its wording from the undelivered address The Tramp and Strike Question. Nonetheless, it reflects themes present in the address eventually published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ).
  - The idea of reconciliation, 1850-1855; loc.05180; xxx.00526; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder [Before 1882], "The Tramp and Strike Questions")
    The second paragraph contained in this manuscript would appear, with revisions, in the beginning of the penultimate paragraph of the Preface to the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - [It will seem strange], 1882-1886; loc.05244; xxx.00467; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder Robert Burns as Poet and Person)
    This prose scrap alludes to both Rabelais and Robert Burns. Here, Whitman describes Burns' principle qualities as "animal appetites, lusts, and bibulousness." In his essay, Robert Burns as Poet and Person, Whitman notes that Burns' poetry includes "lyrics of illicit loves and carousing intoxication." This essay, with the preliminary title of Robert Burns first appeared in The Critic ( 16 December 1882 ), but this particular phrase does not appear in the essay Robert Burns as Poet and Person until its publication in The North American Review 143 ( November 1886 ), 429. This essay was later reprinted in Democratic Vistas and Other Papers ( 1888 ) and in November Boughs ( 1888 ). The essay was also retained, still within November Boughs, in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Burns says, 1882-1886; loc.05247; xxx.00467; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder Robert Burns as Poet and Person)
    This prose scrap quotes a March 1792 letter from Robert Burns to George Thompson. In the essay Robert Burns as Poet and Person, Whitman cites letters to Thompson, particularly letters where Burns discusses his own early love poetry. This scrap is not directly quoted in the essay, but there are allusions to it. The letters are not mentioned in the preliminary publication of the essay, under the title Robert Burns, which appeared in The Critic ( 16 December 1882; however, Thompson's letters figure in the essay Robert Burns as Poet and Person published in The North American Review 143 ( November 1886 ), 429. This essay was later reprinted in Democratic Vistas and Other Papers ( 1888 ) and in November Boughs ( 1888 ). The essay was also retained, still within November Boughs, in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Though the spare hours, 1884-1888; loc.05263; xxx.00467; prose correspondence handwritten 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder Robert Burns as Poet and Person)
    According to Grier, this scrap was found in an envelope with numerous newspaper clippings about Robert Burns dating from March 25, 1836 to August 9, 1890 (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press], 3, 1140). The notes were apparently intended for a revision to the essay Robert Burns as Poet and Person, which appeared under the title Robert Burns in The Critic ( 16 December 1882 ), and as Robert Burns as Poet and Person in The North American Review ( November 1886 ). This essay was later reprinted in Democratic Vistas and Other Papers ( 1888 ) and in November Boughs ( 1888 ). The essay was also retained, still within November Boughs, in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The letter on the verso is dated June 10, 1884.
  - [(for name?], After 1883; loc.05186; xxx.00469; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American Idiom)
    In this manuscript, Whitman ruminates about a title, presumably for the piece published as Slang in America, first in the North American Review ( November 1885 ), and then in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - [? or Names], After 1884; loc.05187; xxx.00469; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American Idiom)
    In this manuscript, Whitman ruminates about the titles of two articles; one was published as Slang in America, first in the periodical the North American Review in November 1885, and then in November Boughs.
  - [? divide into two], After 1880; loc.05188; xxx.00469; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American Idiom)
    In this manuscript, Whitman considers dividing a draft essay in two. Slang in America, referred to here in a trial title as "Slang and Names in America," was first published in the North American Review ( November 1885 ), and then in November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - [Names and Slang], After 1880; loc.05189; xxx.00469; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American Idiom)
  - In view of that progress, 1884-1887; loc.05321; xxx.00473; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder on religion)
    This scrap is a draft of Whitman's essay Five Thousand Poems, first published in The Critic, number 172, April 16, 1887. It was later reprinted in Democratic Vistas and Other Papers (London, 1888 ), and November Boughs ( 1888 ). The language on this leaf appears nearly verbatim in Five Thousand Poems. On the verso is a partial letter to Whitman from the office of The Critic.
  - On the Religion, 1870-1888; loc.05323; xxx.00486; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder on religion)
    The spirit of this note made it into the Lingering Note at the end of Whitman's essay Elias Hicks, Notes (such as they are) in November Boughs ( 1888 ). Apparently, Whitman intended to write a longer essay which did not allude to Hicks. Grier dates this scrap from the 1870s because of the steadiness of the handwriting (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press], 6, 2101).
  - N.W. Texas, Utah, New Mexico, 1879-1882; loc.05339; xxx.00875; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder On the Western United States)
    This scrap is alluded to in the section of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) entitled Steam-Power, Telegraphs, & America's Back-Bone. It was probably composed after September 1879, when Whitman traveled out to Denver, CO. On the verso is a page from an elections inspector's book from the 1850 s.
  - This western two-thirds, 1879-1882; loc.05340; xxx.00876; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder On the Western United States)
    This scrap is alluded to in the section of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) entitled The Prairies and Great Plains in Poetry. It was probably composed after September 1879, when Whitman traveled out to Denver, CO. On the verso is a page from an elections inspector's book from the 1850 s.
  - New American pictures, 1879-1882; loc.05341; xxx.00877; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder On the Western United States)
    This scrap is alluded to in the section of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ) entitled Steam-Power, Telegraphs, & America's Back-Bone. It was probably composed after September 1879, when Whitman traveled out to Denver, CO. The verso is a tax bill for someone else dated 1854. Edward Grier and Fredson Bowers theorize that Whitman came upon a large collection of obsolete forms when he started as an editor at the Brooklyn Daily Times in 1857. He used the forms as notepaper for many years.
  - New Mexico Religion Catholic, 1883; loc.05342; xxx.00878; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder On the Western United States)
    A lot of the language of this scrap is taken from page 1238 of Harper's Statistical Gazetteer ( 1855 ). In 1883, Whitman was asked to compose a poem for the 333rd anniversary of the founding of Santa Fe, NM. He responded with a letter that was published in the Philadelphia Press August 5, 1883. It was reprinted in the section of November Boughs ( 1888 ), entitled The Spanish Element in Our Nationality.
  - Voltaire's readable, 1860-1888; loc.05315; xxx.00487; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    This scrap can be linked to the article George Fox and Shakspere in the section entitled Elias Hicks in November Boughs, published 1888. Whitman is referring to a translation of Voltaire's Philosophical Dictionary (Boston: J. P. Mendum, 1852), where the passage on pages 197-198 clearly discusses Quakers or "primitives."
  - Germany, or even Europe, 1890-1891; loc.05316; xxx.00560; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    This manuscript led to a passage published in Have We a National Literature, (North American Review, 152, March 1891 ), and in Good-bye My Fancy 2nd Annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1891 ), in the section entitled American National Literature.
  - The incident of the blowing up, 1862; loc.05317; xxx.00868; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    This scrap contains a passage that is referenced in Whitman's column Brooklyniana published in the Brooklyn Standard on February 8, 1862. The column is reproduced here.
  - The wreck of the "Mexico", 1882; loc.05318; xxx.00872; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    This scrap refers to the 1836 wreck of the Mexico. Whitman writes about this in the passage Paumanok, and My Life on It as a Child and a Young Man, published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ). According to Grier, the wrecks of the Mexico and the Bristol are also alluded to in The Sleepers, section 4. The scrap dates from December 1882, Grier says, because the address on the verso is that of Robert Pearsall Smith, whom Whitman met then (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts, ed. Edward F. Grier [New York: New York University Press, 1984 ] 3: 1186).
  - See page 81, 1884-1885; loc.05320; xxx.00474; xxx.00873; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)